# Thomas W. Kupferer, Jr.

Healthcare & Technology Professional

Cleveland Heights, OH, 44118, USA (618) 558-5369 twk29@case.edu

https://www.linkedin.com/in/thomaskupfererjr/

# **Professional Profile**

Healthcare and technology professional with over 20 years of experience and a strong foundation in the health informatics industry. Backgrounds in healthcare and technology informed a deep understanding of patient care, complemented by technical proficiencies in EHR systems, statistical analysis, and programming with Python, R, SQL, Minitab, and C++. Committed to applying this multifaceted skill set to drive innovation and growth in health informatics as a doctoral student.

### **Education**

05/2021 – 12/2023	Master of Science, Health Informatics University of Illinois Chicago — Chicago, IL	• 3.85 GPA
01/2017 - 12/2017	Computer Science & Programming McKendree University - Lebanon, IL	<ul><li>3.52 GPA</li><li>Completed 8 credit hours</li></ul>
08/2012 - 02/2016	Osteopathic Medical School University of Pikeville - KCOM - Pikeville, KY	<ul><li>Withdrew to pursue health informatics career</li><li>Completed 107 credit hours</li></ul>
06/2009 – 05/2012	<b>Pre-Med, Biomedical Science</b> Southern Illinois University - Carbondale, IL	<ul><li>3.41 GPA</li><li>Completed 77 credit hours</li></ul>
08/2005 – 05/2007	Master of Arts: Higher Education Administration New York University - New York, NY	• 3.63 GPA
08/1998 – 05/2003	Bachelor of Arts: Psychology McKendree University - Lebanon, IL	• 3.585 GPA

#### **Doctoral Research Interests**

To research and develop cutting-edge solutions that address the following:

- **The Opioid Crisis**: Development of predictive models with response mechanisms and feedback systems using data aggregation with real-time analysis, integration, and communication interfaces
- **Population Health Crises**: Strategizing data-driven approaches and technological innovations to manage and mitigate impacts of widespread health emergencies like the COVID-19 pandemic
- EHR Interoperability: Innovating seamless health data exchange solutions across various EHR platforms

# **Professional & Research Experience**

#### 08/2024 – *Present*

#### Ph.D. Student and Research Assistant

Case Western Reserve University - Cleveland, OH

- Complete first-year research lab rotation prior to selection of mentor and lab for duration of PhD program
- Conduct cohort study on the incidence and prevalence of opioid overdose events in patients with major depressive disorder or bipolar disorder.

#### 07/2019 - 07/2024

## Marketing Data Analyst & Project Manager

Studio Network Solutions – St. Louis, MO

- Utilized market research tools and techniques for comprehensive data analysis
- Conducted data analysis and reports to share insights and support marketing and sales strategies with top-level decision-makers
- Developed data visualization dashboards to streamline stakeholder access to complex data
- Analyzed customer acquisition data and marketing campaign performance, driving efficiency improvements

07/2016 – 07/2019	Samsung Entertainment Expert and Sales Consultant  Best Buy, Edwardsville, IL  Achieved top 5% sales ranking with revamped sales strategies  Applied consultative sales techniques to understand and meet customer needs	
01/2012 - 07/2016	<ul> <li>IT Technician and Medical Assistant</li> <li>Murphysboro Family Medicine Clinic, Murphysboro, IL</li> <li>Implemented and trained staff for electronic medical record system</li> <li>Improved healthcare data management</li> <li>Reviewed patient medical history, used informatics tools for data collection and analysis</li> <li>Diagnosed and solved on-site and remote hardware, software, and network issues</li> </ul>	
05/2010 – 12/2011	<ul> <li>Undergraduate Research Assistant - Physiology</li> <li>Southern Illinois University – Carbondale, Carbondale, IL</li> <li>Conducted genomic research on Rhox homeobox gene cluster</li> <li>Contributed to reproductive cancer-related data</li> <li>Utilized advanced analytical software for data analysis</li> <li>Maintained rigorous data documentation</li> </ul>	
08/2009 – 10/2011	<ul> <li>IT Technical Support Specialist</li> <li>Southern Illinois University - Carbondale, Carbondale, IL</li> <li>Explained technical information in accessible terms to non-technical users</li> <li>Resolved diverse technical issues across multiple systems and applications</li> <li>Promoted efficient resolution of system issues</li> </ul>	
Accomplishments		
05/2007	<ul> <li>Arch Award, New York University</li> <li>Given to one graduating master's student for record of service to school, faculty, and students</li> <li>Presented by Dr. Mary Brabeck, Dean of the Steinhardt School of Culture, Education, &amp; Human Development</li> </ul>	
05/2003	Who's Who Among American College Students, McKendree University	
05/1999 – 05/2003 06/2000 02/1998	Dean's List (Fall & Spring), McKendree University  Technos International Week Award, Technos International College, Tokyo, Japan  Eagle Scout, Boy Scouts of America	

- Health Informatics Systems Management
- Medical and Biological Knowledge
- Information Technology Infrastructure Design and Components
- SQL, R, Minitab, C++, and Excel
- Research Methods

Skills

• Effective Communication Skills

# **Affiliations**

**2021** – *Present* 

**2021** – *Present* 

**2023** – *Present* 

- American Medical Informatics Association (AMIA)
- The American Health Informatics Management Association (AHIMA)
- The Health Information Management Systems Society (HIMSS)